# 哈喽 大家好 我是王刚
Hello everyone. I’m Wang Gang.
# 本期视频我跟大家分享
In this video I’m going to share with you
# 冷门香料
uncommon spices
# 第一部分是名字中带“姜”的香料
1. spices with “jiang” (ginger) in their names
# 大概有沙姜
which include sand ginger
# 良姜
lesser galangal
# 干姜（脱水姜）
dried ginger
# 黄姜
and turmeric
# 其中沙姜分干沙姜和鲜沙姜
Sand ginger is divided into dried and fresh ones.
# 良姜主要作用于卤水调配
Lesser galangal is mainly used in master stock.
# 干沙姜主要作用于底料炒制
Dried sand ginger is used in hot pot base
# 以及磨成粉制作江湖菜
ground for Jianghu dishes
# 自贡菜中又多用于鸡鸭鱼的去腥增香
or used in Zigong dishes to remove gamey taste and enhance aroma of chicken, duck, or fish
# 干姜其实就是新鲜姜脱水 方便长期储存
Dried ginger is fresh ginger dehydrated for long-term storage
# 黄姜虽然也带“姜”
Turmeric, although having "jiang" (ginger) in their Chinese name
# 但其实只能用作于菜肴的上色
is only used for adding color
# 其中多用于盐焗鸡或者咖喱酱
commonly seen in salt baked chicken and curry paste
# 只作用于天然的着色剂
as a natural coloring
# 第二部分是普通家庭比较少见的香料
2. spices not normally seen in common households
# 大概有檀香
which include sandalwood
# 槟榔片
betel nut slice
# 辛夷
xinyi (flos magnoliae)
# 五加皮
and wujiapi (Eleutherococcus gracilistylus)
# 檀香在大部分场景中磨碎之后燃烧去除异味
Indian sandalwood is usually ground and burnt to eliminate unpleasant smell
# 也能在烹饪中少量的使用
and can also be used for cooking in small doses
# 槟榔片主要用于酱香型调味
Betel nut slice is mainly used for soy-based flavor profile
# 或者酱香卤水调配
or making master stock
# 辛夷又名木兰
Xinyi is also called mulan
# 在餐饮行业中被称为毛桃
or maotao in catering industry
# 是因为形状像未长大的毛桃
because of its peach-like shape
# 大多用于卤水中去腥增香
It is commonly used to remove gamey taste and enhance aroma in master stock.
# 五加皮同样是去异增香
Wujiapi is used to remove unpleasant smell and enhance aroma.
# 味道闻起来有奶香
It smells milky
# 细嚼起来发苦
and gives a bitter taste when chewed
# 卤水中用量以千分比计算
Only a few grams are needed for 1 kg of master stock
# 第三部分分为特殊香味的香料
3. spices with special aroma
# 大概有香茅草 甘松 灵香草 藿香杆
which include lemongrass, gan song(Nardostachys chinensis), ling xiang cao(Lysimachia foenum-graecum Hance), and huo xiang stalk
# 其中香茅草的味道和柠檬的味道非常相似
Lemongrass has a lemon-y flavor
# 所以在餐饮行业中被称为柠檬草
so is called “lemon” grass
# 藿香叶在富顺地区多用于豆花蘸水的点缀
Huo xiang leaves are commonly used as an ornament in douhua (tofu pudding) dipping sauce
# 其中藿香摘去叶子之后也将其晒干
The stalk can be sun-dried
# 作为增香的香料
and used as a spice to enhance aroma
# 甘松的味道极其特殊和强烈
The scent of gan song is distinctive and strong
# 在一般人的嗅觉中会认为此香料为足臭
It smells like stinky feet to most people
# 但在广泛卤水锅中使用之后臭味消失
However, when it is used in common master stock, the smelly odor will disappear
# 反而甘松有压腥的作用
and it can inhibit gamey taste
# 灵香草也有特殊清淡的香味
Ling xiang cao has a special light aroma
# 其作用在卤水中是增香防腐护色
functioning in master stock to enhance aroma, fix color and prolong shelf life
# 黑白胡椒主要区分为
The difference between black pepper and white pepper is that
# 白胡椒是完全成熟后的果实
white pepper is the ripe fruit
# 相反黑胡椒是未成熟的果实
while black pepper is the unripe fruit
# 黑白胡椒为两个不同时段的产物
They are the same fruit in different stages
# 黑胡椒比白胡椒更浓香 且辛辣味略低
Black pepper tastes richer and less spicy than white pepper
# 由于颜色的限制 所以多用于西餐烹饪
and is mainly used in western cuisines
# 其中白胡椒主要为去腥增香增辣
White pepper is used to remove gamey taste, enhance aroma and add spicy
# 多用于中餐烹饪
and is mainly used in Chinese dishes
# 第五是天然上色香料
5. natural coloring spices
# 大概有红黄之分
which can introduce red or yellow color
# 其中有姜黄、红曲米、栀子
Under this category there are turmeric, red yeast rice, and gardenia
# 姜黄为纯黄色
Turmeric adds yellow color
# 红曲米为纯红色 栀子为橙黄色
red yeast rice red, and gardenia orange
# 这三种调色剂运用广泛
These color additives are widely used in food production
# 比如卤水
For example, in master stock
# 蛋糕
cakes
# 饮料等食品加工之类
drinks and so on
# 第六分为最容易混淆的香料
6. confusing spices
# 大概有孜然粒 迷迭香 千里香 小茴香
I.e. cumin seed, rosemary, orange jasmine, and fennel seed
# 其中千里香长得很像缩小版的瓜子
Orange jasmine looks like miniature sunflower seeds
# 小茴香像未成熟的稻谷
Fennel seed looks like unripe paddy rice
# 孜然则以味道更好的区分
Cumin seed stands out by its flavor
# 主要用作于烧烤的撒料
and is mainly used in BBQ sprinkle seasoning
# 迷迭香相比其它三样更细更长
Rosemary is thinner and longer than others
# 有点类似于茶叶
looks like tea leaves
# 因为长相接近
Because of their similarity
# 所以在使用的时候需要区分清楚
these spices need to be clearly distinguished when cooking
# 比如作为烧烤的撒料来说
For example, in BBQ sprinkle seasoning
# 其它三样均无法代替孜然
none of the others can be a substitute for cumin seeds
# 又有几种带壳的香料也很类似
There are some shelled spices look similar as well
# 其中香果、草果、槟榔外形非常相似
Xiang guo (Ligusticum chuanxiong Hort fruit), tsao-ko and betel nut look very much alike
# 只有将其切开之后才能看到其中的不同
and can only be distinguished when cut open
# 槟榔切开之后里面是黑色的籽
Betel nut has a black core inside
# 香果切开之后是白色饱满的果实
xiang guo has a white plump seed
# 草果切开之后是较多的小颗粒籽
And tsao-ko has many small seeds when cut open
# 第七分为夫妻香料 公丁香和母丁香
7. Couple spices - male clove and female clove
# 虽然是夫妻香料
Though are called couple spices
# 但在外观上却相差甚远
they differ in looks
# 公丁香是已开的花蕾
Male clove is known as clove bud
# 母丁香是花蕾后的果实
while female clove refers to clove fruit
# 其中广泛应用的是公丁香
Male clove is most widely used
# 其香味非常的浓烈
Because of its strong flavor
# 用量极少
only a small amount is needed each time
# 第八为慎重使用的香料
8. Spices require use with cautious
# 山楂和当归在烹饪中需要注意用量
The amount of hawthorn and dong quai (Chinese Angelica) used in cooking requires attention
# 当归在卤水中起到去异增香
Dong quai is used in master stock to remove unpleasant smell and enhance aroma
# 山楂开胃解腻消食
Hawthorn can stimulate appetite, refresh palate and promote digestion
# 其中当归有活血化瘀的功效
Dong quai can improve blood circulation and transform stasis
# 所以含有这两样香料加工过的食材
so pregnant women should be careful
# 孕妇慎用
with food containing these two spices
# 第九部分是主攻甘甜味的香料
9. Spices that add sweetness
# 其中有罗汉果和甘草
include luo han guo (monk fruit) and licorice
# 罗汉果在使用过程中水会变成褐色
Luo han guo will turn water into brown color
# 所以在卤水中需要考虑到颜色的把控
thus, when luo han guo presents, the color of master stock needs to be considered
# 罗汉果和甘草在卤水中可以调节苦味和涩味
Luo han guo and licorice can neutralize bitter and astringent tastes in master stock
# 在生活中我个人也经常用罗汉果泡开水喝
I often make a luo han guo tea by steeping luo han guo in hot water
# 第十部分我们来介绍价格差异最大的香料陈皮
10. Largest price difference in spice - dried mandarin peel
# 陈皮就像白酒一样
Dried mandarin peel is like baijiu
# 年份越久 价格越贵
the price of which increases with age
# 昂贵的陈皮每斤能达到6位数以上
The price of dried mandarin peel can be more than one million yuan per jin (0.5kg)
# 一般普通的陈皮10元1斤左右
while normal price is about 10 yuan per jin (0.5kg)
# 最后跟大家分享五香粉和五香卤料
Lastly, I’m going to share with you Chinese five spice and five spice marinade ingredients
# 五香粉其中香料是
Ingredients in Chinese five spice are
# 红花椒 丁香 八角 小茴香 桂皮组合而成
red Sichuan peppercorn, clove, star anise, fennel seed, and cinnamon
# 然后再简单的跟大家分享一个五香卤料包
Then the recipe of five spice marinade ingredients includes
# 其中有香叶 甘草 草果 白寇
bay leaf, licorice, tsao-ko, white cardamom,
# 甘松 丁香 香果 小茴香 排草
gan song, clove, xiang guo, fennel seed, xiang pai cao,
# 白芷 荜拨 香砂仁 桂皮 八角
baizhi, long pepper, Cardamom Seed, cinnamon, and star anise
# 此配方介于家用和商用之间
This recipe is for either domestic or commercial use
# 所以五香卤料只是一个名称
Chinese five spice is a name
# 而不是由香料的品种数量来决定
rather than naming the number of spices.
# 香料介绍完毕，后续会以香料制作卤水，敬请期待
That is all for spice introduction. Applying spices in master stock is coming soon.